welcome to this launch event session on
what's new in data search Improvement
particularly targeting developers my
name is Jens M Peterson and I'm an
engineering manager in the business
Central
team first what is modern search well in
this release we have added a method to
search for all words rather than any
substring in a word it's a significantly
faster way of searching and it also
tends to match more what you've gotten
to expect from other search
engines and this applies this new search
mechanism applies to Page search lookup
and companywide
search the way you enable your data to
be searched using modern search
is that you use the new property
optimized for text search equals true on
your table Fields you can put it on your
table fields or you can put it on your
table extension
Fields you would want to add this to the
following types of fields the primary
key Fields descriptive text fields that
uniquely describes this item or other
fields identifying the row which could
be a name or something and generally you
should add this to fields that the users
want to find not to fields which where
there are thousands of them or where
it's a grouping mechanism so let's take
a look at how this actually looks in the
product first you may want to check that
you actually have this feature enabled
you do that in feature management
and in here you can see this line use
optimize text search in
lists and in this case it is
enabled all right so with this enable
let's take a look at how it
works so if I go to
items and in this case I have filled up
the database with half a million random
items to actually see the performance
difference between the two so if I look
for beans
roasted notice the speed and also note
that the ordering of words doesn't
matter so now it has found all the whole
roasted beans or
Colombia now if we were to do this or if
I want to find for
Brazil this is it it finds it now the
user can switch between the two two
types of search because you can enable
Legacy
search and now it actually takes a while
because now it actually tries to search
I just want to do that again and it
actually doesn't find it in this case
because there was a comma between beans
and Brazil so in order to find it using
Legacy search you would need to actually
type the comma so there is a performance
difference where I would expect users to
feel this the most is in sales
orders if I go down to a sales order
down
here and I now need to type in an item
I'm just going to delete the existing
item and first I'm going to try using
Legacy search so now I'm going to type
beans comma
Brazil and you can see it takes a little
while you actually get the spinning
wheel you still have the spinning wheel
and now it has found it now let's try
the same thing with modern search I'm
just going
to delete this and now I'm going to type
again beans
Brazil and you can see that it's a lot
faster now you might have some users who
are used to typing in parts of an ID I
know that in this data set there is a
button which is sp- bomb 1303 and there
might be users that are used to just
typing 1303 so we've actually made it
possible to switch directly by using the
star star 1303 this will search in the
Legacy way so it is a bit slower but it
will actually find the SP bomb
1303 a third place where you can see
modern search in action is when you
search company data if I go for B means
Brazil and I search company
data it has already found these items
because it uses the new modern search
but also
here you can type a star to actually get
the old behavior and I need to start the
search and that takes a little longer
and it actually also found some
customers with
1303 the modern search is enabled on in
Page search when the table has optimized
for text search fields and the user can
select the behavior using the
drop-down or by typing
star modern search also shows up in
lookup if the table has optimized for
teex search fields and the again the
user can select and this time this time
using the co wheel in the lookup page or
by typing
star and modern search is enabled in
when you search in company data where it
will use modern search for Fields with
optimized for Tech search but if you
include fields which are not part of the
tech search index then you will still
get the other behav the existing
behavior and unfortunately also the
existing performance again you can use
the contain search by typing the star
under the hood what happens is that the
synchronization engine which updates the
SQL schema will generate a full text
search index and regenerated it whenever
the list of indexed fields change it'll
create one index per table with indexed
fields we are creating this as a neutral
language index meaning we only have the
standard word
breakers for instance space and dash so
it is not language dependent if you want
to know more about how full teex search
works in general you can see the link
here at the bottom which is a link to
the documentation for full teex search
in
SQL now you might wonder why this is so
much faster well the Legacy search does
a case insensitive contain
search so it basically makes it possible
for SQL Server to use indexes so it
always requires you to read the full
table or the full index to find it and
you will have seen this in Long running
queries Telemetry where you see queries
with collate statements which normally
comes from the Page search functionality
the modern search on the other hand
Builds an index on every word and now
you have an index lookup into those
words and in general index lookups are
just an order of magnitude
faster now it's not only in the UI that
you can make use of modern search you
can also use it on the record API it is
built into the set filter method so you
can now use the new operator and and for
calling set filter there is an example
down here field ref. set filter and and
and string star it will find a matching
word if you want to find a beginning of
a word you add a wild card at the end
the star which has been done
here
if the field you're searching is not one
of those which have optimized for text
search equals true then it'll revert
back to the existing Behavior using case
insensitive contain
search which where you can see the
Syntax for here here now if you want to
see how this actually how this syntax
actually looks let's take a look at the
the product again in order to see the
syntax of set filter you can make use of
the page inspection pane over here you
can see the page filters and you can see
the filters that the UI actually applies
when you use the Page
search if I type beans here
you can see over here that the filter
term on the the number field and the
description field is and and beans Star
as we talked about before and if I do
beans
brail then you can now see the double
end and then there's an end in between
and the double end with both beans and
Brazil so it can get a little involved
but this is a good way to play around to
actually see the actual
syntax there are some considerations
when you use the double and filter
operator for using the text search first
of all the syntax can be a little hard
to grasp you saw the trick with using
the page inspector to show the generated
filters you can see samples of the code
in the data search and table code
unit the scenarios where you want to use
this would be where you implement
specific features for helping the user
finding elements you would normally
avoid using this for explicit business
logic where you're better off using
existing equals filters Etc also because
the behavior here changes based on
whether the user has enabled This Modern
search and also on whether the field has
been optimized for Tech search with that
I hope you'll get a lot of fun out of
the modern search and that your
customers will be happy with the
improved performance thank you